<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-13T12:02:16+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Gharda Derrian Tradewa</title><entry><title type="html">Problem Solving in the Real (Working) World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/business/2024/04/13/problem-solving.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Problem Solving in the Real (Working) World" /><published>2024-04-13T11:45:10+07:00</published><updated>2024-04-13T11:45:10+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/business/2024/04/13/problem-solving</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/business/2024/04/13/problem-solving.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>No ChatGPT is used in the making of this article</em></p>

<p>Problem solving is one of the most important skills anyone in the working world can have. However, it is highly misunderstood due to its broad meaning and applications. People has been sticking “problem solving” to anything, any answer to any questions, that make even the smallest progress to current problem. In this article, I want to talk about a more specific kind of problem solving which has been discussed thoroughly in this book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6271219-problem-solving-101">Problem Solving 101</a>.</p>

<p>What is problem solving? Problem solving is a method that is applied to complex and ambiguous problem in order to tame it and make it easier to solve. Most of the time, complex problem are just easy problems stacked on top of each other. If we have the tools and capability to dissect the big problem into smaller more manageable problem, we can solve most problems. So, how do we do problem solving?</p>

<h5 id="step-1-understand-really-understand-the-problem-statement"><strong>Step 1: Understand, really understand, the problem statement</strong></h5>
<p>The single most critical step in problem solving is to really understand the problem you are trying to solve. Often, people solve problem they don’t really understand and they end up solving different problem altogether. Believe me or not, sometimes the owner of the problem (for example your boss in the office who assigns you to do the problem solving) do not even have good grasps on the problem to solve himself. Therefore, you really need to clarify the problem at hand to your boss. This step can often trigger the problem owner to really think what problem he/she want to solve. One advice for understanding the problem statement is to try to formulate the problem in simple mathematical equation so you can agree on the metrics for the success of the problem solving</p>

<h5 id="step-2-break-the-ultimate-problem-into-smaller-components"><strong>Step 2: Break the ultimate problem into smaller components</strong></h5>
<p>Often enough the main problem that we are facing is too high level and abstract to be acted upon. For example: <em>“How can we increase revenue for our groceries line of business?”</em>. If we try to answer this directly we will spit out the most general answer with no direct action at all. It is much more helpful to first breakdown revenue problem to volume and price (this is too simple of a model but works for now). Example of problem breakdown:</p>
<ul>
  <li>How can we increase volume?
    <ul>
      <li>How can we increase transacting user?
        <ul>
          <li>How can we increase user acquisition?</li>
          <li>How can we increase active existing user?</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>How can we increase purchase frequency?
        <ul>
          <li>What product is the most popular? Can we push further its sales?</li>
          <li>Should we create a next-order promotion?</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>How can we increase average order value?
        <ul>
          <li>Can we create package promotion to increase number of purchased items?</li>
          <li>Can we promote a more expensive items?</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>How can we increase price?</li>
</ul>

<p>By breaking down the ultimate problem we are faced with a smaller, easier, and a more direct problem to solve as listed above.</p>

<h5 id="step-3-actually-solve-the-problem"><strong>Step 3: Actually solve the problem</strong></h5>
<p>If we already have simple enough problem to solve directly we can just go out and solve the problem. We can create hypothesis testing to prove/disprove certain hypothesis, we can collect data to support our hypothesis. After we have conclusion we can do the most appropriate action based on the conclusion. Do not forget in business the action is what actually matters.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="business" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[No ChatGPT is used in the making of this article]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review: What is Life? by Erwin Schrödinger</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/book/review/2024/04/08/what-is-life.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: What is Life? by Erwin Schrödinger" /><published>2024-04-08T21:18:10+07:00</published><updated>2024-04-08T21:18:10+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/book/review/2024/04/08/what-is-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/book/review/2024/04/08/what-is-life.html"><![CDATA[<p>How is life influenced by the laws of physics? This question was put forward by Erwin Schrödinger in his book <em>What is Life?</em>. Finding out the interconnection, or rather, the influence of physics as the fundamental laws in nature towards biological processes is his main goal in this book.</p>

<p>He starts the conversation by stating that every organism is significantly bigger than atoms. This leads to the idea that the physics that influences the life of organisms is largely based on statistical physics, while quantum mechanics interaction is negligible. One other supporting argument for  this is quantum mechanics, with its randomness, is unlikely to influence organisms because we did not see living organisms randomly change all the time. </p>

<p>However, the discovery of chromosomes cancelled out the idea that quantum mechanics interaction can be totally neglected in living matters. With such small size, chromosomes must have been influenced by the laws of quantum mechanics. So how does chromosome stay permanent? More importantly, is it necessary for chromosomes to stay permanent? It is indeed necessary for a chromosome to stay stable and permanent to ensure the consistent growth of an organism through two different mechanisms. First, through mitosis where a cell divides and duplicates to create a perfect copy of itself including its pair of chromosomes. Second, through meiosis where a cell divides itself and only brings with them one part of chromosomes and gets ready for fertilisation.</p>

<p>Chromosomes as the blueprint of living matters that are being passed throughout generations, change, vary, and evolve. The variations can come from small, slow, and continuous variations due to natural selection or from mutation due to quantum mechanics. Mutation happens due to quantum jumps in the gene molecule triggered by X-rays or due to random jumps in quantum mechanics. The popular idea that the slow and small variations are inherited is wrong and mutation is actually the variations that will be inherited through generations.</p>

<p>So how do chromosomes stay permanent despite being in the size that can be influenced by quantum mechanics and situated in the hot environment inside the body of living matter? One possible reason is that it takes a lot of excitation energy to change the structure of the current gene to the next structure with a different energy state. It is known from the theory of quantum mechanics that to bring one system from a particular energy state to the next the system requires energy that is higher than the next energy state.</p>

<p>The notion that chromosomes should be treated as molecules (Delbrück’s model) and thus follow the law of quantum mechanics raise a debate between biologists. Erwin, as the supporter of quantum mechanics theory, said that quantum mechanics is the fundamental theory of all atoms in nature and there is no alternative to explain the physics that govern chromosome molecules. The adversaries of the quantum mechanics theory argue by throwing such a question “Are there no other endurable structures composed of atoms except molecules? For example a gold coin buried in a tomb for a thousand years, preserving the traits of the portrait stamped on it.” The answer to this question is that the underlying mechanism between molecules and a gold coin is actually similar. Both gold coins, chromosomes, and crystals are solid states that are bonded by Heitler-London bondage and it requires a lot of excitation energy to change the structures of these solids. He also brought the idea that the molecule inside the cells is aperiodic solid which is different from periodic solid with repeatable structure that is commonly found in the inanimate object. Due to reasons above, we can conclude that Delbrück’s model stands the test and can be used in further considerations.</p>

<p>The order that is observed in the gene is different from the order-from-disorder which is observed in a macroscopic level such as a drop of milk in the water which is diluted and creates a seemingly “ordered” system that comes from the disorder of all the involving water and milk molecules. The order in living matter comes from the molecules in the gene which govern the life of the living matter. This gene molecule is in itself is in order, stable, and unbothered by randomness that happens in the quantum mechanical environment. The possible reason for this maintained orderliness, which causes living matter to evade going into the state of disorder (death), is by consuming negative entropy from the environment.</p>

<p>Living matter is unmatched by anything inanimate in its degree of orderliness by evading the random and unpredictable mechanism of the quantum mechanics world. The stability of the gene is so prominent and unprecedented that it is as if this matter is purely mechanical and unbothered by randomness in nature. In a normal matter such as in a chemical reaction, we can never deterministically know which atom will undergo a reaction first. The regularity of normal matters is only observable in the macroscopic view of the system. In biology a single, tiny group of atoms which govern the process and life of the living matter is seemingly governed by a different mechanism which neglects the randomness and unpredictability that occurs at the atomic level. Nevertheless, this orderliness and seemingly a purely mechanical system is not entirely new to physics as we can reflect (approximately) from the motion of planets around the sun and the motion of a good pendulum clock which is not impacted by heat and statistical mechanics. These systems work as if they are situated in the absolute zero temperature where the impact of statistical physics is non-existent. In this case living matters resemble the situation of a clockwork which is strong enough to withstand heat motion and quantum mechanics phenomenon.</p>

<p>In conclusion, Erwin Schrödinger argued that living matter, and chromosomes in general, is indeed influenced and governed by the law of quantum mechanics. However, the stability of the gene is so prominent and unprecedented that it is as if this matter is purely mechanical and unbothered by randomness in nature. This astonishing mechanism led Erwin to question whether a new law of physics is necessary to explain the orderliness of genes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How is life influenced by the laws of physics? This question was put forward by Erwin Schrödinger in his book What is Life?. Finding out the interconnection, or rather, the influence of physics as the fundamental laws in nature towards biological processes is his main goal in this book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Indonglish</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/english/2015/11/09/indonglish.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indonglish" /><published>2015-11-09T21:18:10+07:00</published><updated>2015-11-09T21:18:10+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/english/2015/11/09/indonglish</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/english/2015/11/09/indonglish.html"><![CDATA[<p>Sebagai kaum pribumi Indonesia yang hampir seluruh hidupnya dihabiskan di kota besar, bahasa Inggris tidak lagi asing untuk saya. Di berbagai sudut kehidupan perkotaan dengan mudahnya ditemukan bahasa Inggris. Bahasa adidaya ini dipergunakan untuk advertensi, pengumuman event-event gaul anak muda, situs-situs lokal, dan yang paling tidak bisa lepas dari kita, ponsel.</p>

<p>Sebagai kaum pribumi Indonesia yang mendapat kesempatan untuk studi di negeri Belanda, saya mengamati suatu fenomena menarik bahwa pengaruh bahasa Inggris di Indonesia lebih kuat daripada di Belanda. Padahal Belanda adalah salah satu dari negara dengan rata-rata nilai TOEFL tertinggi di dunia (selama disini hanya 2 orang yang saya ketahui tidak kenal bahasa Inggris, dan umur mereka mungkin sudah sekitar 70-an). Di Belanda sini, penggunaan bahasa lokal masih sangat kental. Saya rasa di Jerman atau Prancis kondisi penggunaan bahasa lokal ini lebih parah lagi. Satu contoh lucu adalah penyebutan singkatan seperti PC, yang di Indonesia adalah pi-si, menjadi pe-se di Belanda, atau CD, yang di Indonesia adalah si-di dan di Belanda adalah se-de. Di kantor tempat saya magang sekarang contohnya, user interface mesin printer menggunakan bahasa belanda. Laptop dari kantor pun default-nya menggunakan bahasa Belanda. Begitu pula dengan ponsel teman-teman Belanda sekalian.</p>

<p>Pengaruh lebih jauh dari bahasa Inggris di Indonesia adalah kebiasaan mendeskripsikan sesuatu dalam bahasa Inggris, entah itu karena kurangnya padanan kata-kata di bahasa Inggris dalam bahasa Indonesia, atau memang padanan kata yang tepat kurang populer. Pada dasarnya memang banyak kata-kata yang jauh lebih mudah dan lebih “dapat diterima” dalam percakapan jika kita menggunakan bahasa Inggris. Berikut salah satu contoh:</p>

<p>lu kalo mau jadi orang hebat harus bisa survive</p>

<p>Bandingkan dengan</p>

<p>lu kalo mau jadi orang hebat harus bisa bertahan (hidup)</p>

<p>Ada contoh lain yang jika kita menggunakan bahasa Indonesia sesungguhnya tidak terlalu aneh, tetapi istilah dalam bahasa Inggris lebih sering dipakai. Contoh:</p>

<p>Suara lu annoyying banget sih</p>

<p>Daripada</p>

<p>Suara lu mengganggu banget sih</p>

<p>Contoh lain adalah kata-kata default yang telah saya gunakan pada paragraf kedua. Sesungguhnya saya tidak tahu kata Indonesia apa yang cocok untuk dipadankan disitu. Payah.</p>

<p>Disini saya tidak akan memberi himbauan-himbauan klise kepada sudara-sudara untuk lebih mencintai bahasa Indonesia bla bla bla. Karena saya pun merasa cukup sulit jika harus menggunakan padanan kata dalam bahasa Indonesia untuk bahasa Inggris yang sudah kadung populer. Bahkan saya kesulitan ketika untuk menggunakan bahasa Indonesia di ponsel.</p>

<p>Tujuan saya menulis hal ini adalah untuk memberikan pertanyaan yang sudah beberapa kali saya pikirkan. Apa di masa depan nanti bahasa Indonesia akan menciut karena banyak kata yang tergantikan oleh bahasa Inggris, dan apakah akan berakibat buruk pada masa depan negeri kita? Toh, tujuan utama komunikasi itu you understand I understand. Atau akankah bahasa Indonesia dapat dikategorikan sebagai budaya yang oleh karena itu harus dilestarikan? While in the meantime, bahasa Indonesia di sekolahan bukan favorit kebanyakan orang, dan saya dulu.</p>

<p>Eindhoven,
9 November 2015,
Habis dota, sebelah toples salsa, sebelah tiket MU, hareupeun laptop, tukangen sofa, udud beak, rek meuli mahal.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="english" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sebagai kaum pribumi Indonesia yang hampir seluruh hidupnya dihabiskan di kota besar, bahasa Inggris tidak lagi asing untuk saya. Di berbagai sudut kehidupan perkotaan dengan mudahnya ditemukan bahasa Inggris. Bahasa adidaya ini dipergunakan untuk advertensi, pengumuman event-event gaul anak muda, situs-situs lokal, dan yang paling tidak bisa lepas dari kita, ponsel.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Polymath: They Who Know a Lot about a Lot</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/knowledge/2014/02/25/polymath-they-who-know-a-lot-about-a-lot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Polymath: They Who Know a Lot about a Lot" /><published>2014-02-25T21:18:10+07:00</published><updated>2014-02-25T21:18:10+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/knowledge/2014/02/25/polymath-they-who-know-a-lot-about-a-lot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/knowledge/2014/02/25/polymath-they-who-know-a-lot-about-a-lot.html"><![CDATA[<p>Polymath disini tidak berhubungan (langsung) dengan matematika, termasuk polygon atau polynomial, mentang-mentang ada kata-kata poly nya, ada kata math nya.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A polymath (Greek: πολυμαθής, polymathēs, “having learned much” is a person whose expertise spans a significant number of different subject areas; such a person is known to draw on complex bodies of knowledge to solve specific problems. The term was first used in the seventeenth century but the related term, polyhistor, is an ancient term with similar meaning.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Tokoh-tokoh zaman Islamic Golden Age dan Renaissance banyak yang termasuk dalam lingkungan para manusia pintar dan langka (di masa sekarang) ini. Seorang titisan dewa yang saya yakin anda kenal adalah Leonardo da Vinci. Saking tersohornya nama orang ini, di game Assassin’s Creed dia muncul sebagai insinyur pemasok senjata sang tokoh utama disamping melukis di waktu senggangnya. Tokoh ini adalah salah satu tokoh mahsyur di masa Renaissance.</p>

<p>Di masa Islamic Golden Age di masa kejayaan islam, tidak seperti sekarang dimana kebanyakan kita berkutat dengan perang saudara, kelaparan, dan kemiskinan, banyak pula ilmuwan polymath macam ini, salah satunya adalah Ibnu Sina atau yang terkenal di dunia barat Avicenna. Ibnu Sina ini adalah seorang ahli medis yang juga filsuf yang juga ahli matematika dll. Masih banyak nama-nama polymath lain seperti ibn Haytham, al khwarizmi.</p>

<p>Polymath ini menurut saya adalah salah satu tren ilmuwan jaman dulu yang pengen belajar apa saja, tau apa saja, ditanya apa saja bisa jawab. Bahkan kadang keilmuannya ada dari bidang yang keliatannya ga nyambung sama sekali. Contohnya aja si da Vinci yang engineer besar sekaligus artist nomor wahid. Mungkin semacam anda fusionkan Pak Habibie sama Pak Affandi Koesoema terus anda fusionkan lagi sama arsitek, pematung, dan lain lain. (Untuk yang ga tau “fusion” coba googling dengan keyword “fusion dragon ball”)</p>

<p>Tapi hari-hari kejayaan polymath habis sudah. Keberadaan semakin langka, mereka mungkin tak bisa hidup seribu tahun lagi seperti binatang jalang yang terbuang, mungkin karena ilmu semakin berkembang sehingga sulit untuk mendalami banyak ragam ilmu sekaligus, atau sistem sekarang yang lebih nyaman dengan keadaan seperti itu. Kalau kita oot sedikit ada beberapa keadaan yang menurut saya menghambat lahirnya polymath-polymath baru yang akan saya bahas berdasarkan pengalaman pribadi yaitu pengalaman di kalangan akar rumput. Di kalangan akar rumput, seperti contohnya saat saya kuliah dulu, banyak orang yang mengasosiasikan dirinya dengan bidang A dan melepaskan diri dari bidang selain A dan menganggap dirinya tidak akan bisa mempelajari ilmu di luar bidang A. Sejujurnya, saya kadang seperti itu juga hehe. Mungkin darah muda namanya, fanatisme golongan.</p>

<p>Menurut pandangan pribadi saya, it’s cool to be a polymath or having a polymath in the neighborhood, but just for the sake of the uniqueness, karena saya juga ga tahu apa untungnya seseorang jadi polymath atau bukan bagi masyarakat, kalau untuk dianya sendiri ya jelas untung karena tau banyak, tau banyak ya bisa ngasih tau orang banyak, dan ngasih tau orang banyak itu pahalanya banyak.</p>

<p>By the way, artikel ini menjelaskan tentang hari-hari terakhir dari para polymath.</p>

<p>Shalom.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="knowledge" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Polymath disini tidak berhubungan (langsung) dengan matematika, termasuk polygon atau polynomial, mentang-mentang ada kata-kata poly nya, ada kata math nya.]]></summary></entry></feed>